<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mothers counsell or, liue within compasse Being the last will and testament to her dearest daughter.</title>
            <author>M. R.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10300</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20583</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101922</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837725</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837725</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2065</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10300)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2065)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1033:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mothers counsell or, liue within compasse Being the last will and testament to her dearest daughter.</title>
                  <author>M. R.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 42 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For Iohn Wright, and are to be sold at his shop in spur street without Newgate, at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1630?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Good counsell to the Christian reader" signed: M. R.</note>
                  <note>Publication date suggested by STC. Title page reads: 163.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page mutilated, affecting imprint.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mothers and daughters --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Young women --  Religious life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2065:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2065:1"/>
            <p>The Mothers Counſell OR, Liue within Compaſſe. Being the
laſt Will and Teſtament to her deareſt Daughter.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Modesty</head>
               <p> 
                  <list>
                     <item>In Chaſtitie. Chaſtity of body is the key to Relig.
Wanto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</item>
                     <item>In Temperance. Temperance is the mother o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>In Beautie.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>ry is a womans golden Crowne.
Odio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                     <item>In Humilitie. Humilitie is a womans beſt Armor.
Pride.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>Iohn Wright,</hi> and are to be
ſold at his Shop in ſpur ſtreet without Newgate, at the ſigne of the
Bible. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2065:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2065:2"/>
            <head>Good Counſell to the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 THat you keepe a narrow watch ouer your heart, words, and
deedes conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually.</item>
               <item>2 That with all care the time be redeemed that hath been
idly, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly, and vnprofitably ſpent.</item>
               <item>3 That once in the day at leaſt, priuate prayer, and
meditation bee made.</item>
               <item>4 That care be had to doe, and receiue good in
company.</item>
               <item>5 That your family be with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and regard,
inſtructed, wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ouer, &amp; Chriſtianly gouerned.</item>
               <item>6 That no more care bee ſpent in matters of this world,
then muſt needs.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2065:3"/>7 That you ſtirre vp your ſelue to
liberalitie to Gods Saints.</item>
               <item>8 That you prepare your ſelues to beare the Croſſe, by
what meanes ſoeuer it ſhall pleaſe God to exerciſe you.</item>
               <item>9 That you giue not the leaſt bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to wandring
thoughts.</item>
               <item>10 That you beſtow ſome time in mourning, not onely for
your owne ſinnes, but for the time and age wherein you liue.</item>
               <item>11 That you looke daily for the comming of our Lord Jeſus
Chriſt, for your full deliuerance out of this world.</item>
               <item>12 That you acquaint your ſelues with ſome godly
perſon, with whom you may conferre of your Chriſtian eſtate, and open
your doubts, to the quickning of Gods graces in you.</item>
            </list>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2065:3"/>
            <head>The Mothers counſell, OR, Liue within Compaſſe. Being the
laſt Will and Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to her deareſt Daughter, which may ſerue for a
worthy Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to all the Women in the World, which deſire good report from
men in this world, and grace from Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus in the laſt day.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Liue within Compaſſe: In Chaſtitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt my Daughter vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that Chaſtity is the
beautie of the ſoule and puritie of life, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth the corrupt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſures of the fleſh:
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> onely poſſeſſed of
thoſe who ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:2065:4"/> bodies
cleane and vndefiled; and it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth either in ſincere virginitie, or
in faithfull Matrimony.</p>
               <p>The chaſte ſoule is a rich chamber, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fit for
Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The moſt bountifull God is a chaſte and pure Spirit, and
therefore aboue all things thou oughteſt to call vpon him with chaſte
prayers.</p>
               <p>If the body be not kept pure and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted from whoredome,
the Soule can hardly be feruent in deuout prayer.</p>
               <p>Pure chaſtity is beauty to the Soule, grace to the body, and
peace to all wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy deſires.</p>
               <p>Beautie is like the flowers of the Spring, but chaſtitie like
the ſtarres in heauen.</p>
               <p>So muſt the fleſh be nouriſhed, that it may ſerue thee;
ſo muſt it be tamed, that it be not proud.</p>
               <p>As nothing is more vile than to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercommed of the fleſh,
ſo nothing is more glorious, than to ouercome the fleſh.</p>
               <p>Frugalitie is the ſigne of chaſtitie.</p>
               <p>Chaſtity is a vertue of the ſoule, whoſe companion is
fortitude.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2065:4"/>Chaſtity is the Seale of Grace, the ſtaffe
of deuotion, the marke of the Iuſt, the crowne of virginity, the glory of
life, and a comfort in Martyrdome.</p>
               <p>Idleneſſe is the enemy to chaſtity.</p>
               <p>Chaſtity without charity, is
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> without oyle.</p>
               <p>Chaſtity and modeſty are ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to enrich the poore: And
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> age, rather make choyce o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> manners, than looſeneſſe
o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our with great Lands and rich
poſſeſſions.</p>
               <p>If chaſtity bée once loſt, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left
prayſe-worthy in a woman.</p>
               <p>The firſt ſtep to chaſtity, is to know the fault, the
next, to auoyd it.</p>
               <p>Where neceſſitie is ioyned vnto cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, thence
Authoritie is giuen to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe; for neither is ſhe chaſte which
by feare is compelled, neither is ſhée ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt which with
néede is obtained.</p>
               <p>Doe not ſay thou haſte a chaſte minde, if thine eye be
wanton: for a laſciuious looke is a ſigne of an inconſtant heart.</p>
               <p>Amongſt all the conflicts of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſoule, none is
more hard than the warres of a chaſte minde, for the ſight is continuall,
and the victorie rare.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2065:5"/>Chaſtity with the raines of Reaſon
bridleth the rage of luſt.</p>
               <p>A chaſte eare cannot abide to heare that which is
diſhoneſt.</p>
               <p>True felicity though hid from mortall eyes, yet is it the obiect
of a chaſte ſpirit.</p>
               <p>The firſt felicitie that a chaſte woman ſhall haue after
this life, is the reſt of her Soule in Chriſt: the ſecond ſhall be the
immortalitie and glory of her body.</p>
               <p>That chaſte woman hath got to the height of felicitie, whom no
feare trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth, no penſiueneſſe conſumeth, no car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
concupiſcence tormenteth, no deſire of worldly wealth afflicteth, nor any
fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe moueth vnto mirth.</p>
               <p>A chaſte woman is to be meaſured not by her beauties, but by
her vertues.</p>
               <p>A woman is the wonder of Nature if ſhée wrong not
Nature.</p>
               <p>A chaſte woman is an admirable Angell, till ſhée be
drawne by angells to become a Deuill.</p>
               <p>Women that are chaſte when they are truſted, proue often
wantons when they are cauſeleſſe ſuſpected.</p>
               <p>A virgins heart is like the Cotton trée, whoſe fruit is
ſo hard in the Bud, that <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2065:5"/> it ſoundeth like ſteele, and
being ripe puts forth nothing but wooll.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Chaſtitie is a veile which Innocents adorne,</l>
                  <l>th' vngatherd roſe defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded with the thorne.</l>
                  <l>O Chaſtitie the gift of bleſſed ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>comfort in death, a crowne vnto the life,</l>
                  <l>which all the paſſions of the minde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trols,</l>
                  <l>adorne the minde, and beautifies the wife;</l>
                  <l>that grace, the which nor death, nor time attaints,</l>
                  <l>Of earthly Creatures, making heauenly Saints.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Penelope</hi> in ſpending chaſte her dayes,</l>
                  <l>as worthy as <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> was of prayſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Beleee't, a woman cannot take vpon her</l>
                  <l>with Beauty, Riches, nor with hie nobility,</l>
                  <l>to claime the true deſerued praiſe of honor,</l>
                  <l>if chaſtitie doe faile by her fragilitie;</l>
                  <l>for that's the vertue which defends her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor.</l>
                  <l>Chaſtitie is ſtrong, when all that wooe</l>
                  <l>it doth reſiſt, and turnes them vertuous too.</l>
                  <l>Vnchaſte words vtter'd to a vertuous dame,</l>
                  <l>turne and defile the ſpeaker with red ſhame.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:2065:6"/>A Wife is like a garment vſ'd and
torne,</l>
                  <l>A Maid like one made vp, but neuer worne.</l>
                  <l>Gold is not knowne by ſight, but by the teſt:</l>
                  <l>Thought makes not chaſte, but tryall proues them beſt.</l>
                  <l>Misfortune ſtill ſuch proiects doth purſue,</l>
                  <l>He makes a falſe Wife that ſuſpects a true.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Their carriage, not their Chaſtitie alone,</l>
                  <l>Muſt keepe their name chaſte from ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Out of Compaſſe in Chaſtitie, Is
Wantonneſſe.</head>
               <p>WAntonneſſe when it turnes to luſt, in a womans boſome,
is a deſire againſt reaſon, a furious and vnbridled appetite, which
killeth all good motions in her minde, and leaueth no place for vertue.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:2065:6"/>Shame and infamie waits at the héeles
of vnbridled wantons.</p>
               <p>Wantonneſſe is an enemy to the purſe, a foe to the
perſon, a canker to the minde, a corroſiue to the conſcience, a weakner
of the wit, a befotter of the ſenſes, and laſtly, a mortall bane to all
the bodie; ſo that thou ſhalt finde pleaſure is the path-way to
perdition, and wantonneſſe the load-ſtone to ruth and ruine.</p>
               <p>Wantonneſſe maketh a woman co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet beyond her power, to act
beyond her nature, and to die before her time.</p>
               <p>Senſuall and wanton vice hath euer theſe three companions.
Firſt, blindneſſe of vnderſtanding; ſecondly, hardneſſe of heart;
and laſtly, want of Grace and perfection.</p>
               <p>Wantonneſſe is inſeparably accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with the troubling
of order, with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudency, ſloth, and diſſoluteneſſe.</p>
               <p>Adultery deſireth not procreation, but onely pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Wantonneſſe is a ſtrong tower of miſchiefe, and hath in
it many keepers and many defenders, as Needineſſe, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Paleneſſe,
Diſcord, Loue, and Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2065:7"/>Euery good woman makes not for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man a
good wife, no more than one diſh of meat can pleaſe all ſtomackes; but
euery euill woman makes an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute ill wife, as a drop of
<hi>Coloquintida</hi> marres the whole pot of pottage.</p>
               <p>Wanton dwarfe women, or fooliſh ones, are the worſt to make
wiues of; for the firſt brings forth but a race of P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ies, and for the latter, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo
fulſome as a ſhe-foole.</p>
               <p>Wantonneſſe is attended on by riot, and they two impaire
health, conſume wealth, and transforme a woman to a beaſt.</p>
               <p>Wantonneſſe is a ſin of no ſingle rank: No ordinary
ſtation, that neuer walkes vnattended with a traine of miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors at the
heeles.</p>
               <p>Corrupt company is more infections than corrupt aire; therefore
let women be aduiſed in their choiſe; for that text of thy ſelfe that
could neuer bee expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, thy companion ſhall as thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie, lay open
to the world: for it is ſeene by experience, that if thoſe which are
neither good nor euill accompany with thoſe that are good, they are
tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2065:7"/> into their vertue. If thoſe that are
neither good nor euill conſort with thoſe that are euill, they are
incorporated to their vice. If the good companie with the good, both are made
the better; if the euill with the euill, both the worſe; for ſuch as the
companie is, ſuch is the condition.</p>
               <p>There be foure vices a wanton woman is euer moſt troubled
with, ſloathfulneſſe, careleſnes, vaine curioſitie, and
niceneſſe.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hate and Diſdain ſhines in a wantons eyes;</l>
                  <l>Deceit and Treaſon in their boſome lies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Th' are mad that thinke by any meanes to ſtay</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> a wantons mind
that is diſpoſd to ſtray.</l>
                  <l>Such is the crueltie of women kind,</l>
                  <l>when they haue ſhaken off the ſhamefac'ſt band,</l>
                  <l>with which wiſe nature did them ſtrongly bind.</l>
                  <l>t'obey the heſts of mans well ruling hand,</l>
                  <l>that then all rule &amp; reaſon they withſtand,</l>
                  <l>to purchaſe a licentious libertie.</l>
                  <l>But vertuous women wiſely vnderſtand</l>
                  <l>that they were borne to Humilitie,</l>
                  <l>vnleſſe the Heauens them lift to lawfull Soueraigntie.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:2065:8"/>'Tis certaine that the wanton woman
neuer</l>
                  <l>Loues Beautie in her ſexe, but Enuie euer.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There cannot be a greater clog to man,</l>
                  <l>than to be troubled with a wanton woman.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis euermore obſeru'd 'mongſt men,</l>
                  <l>that be ſhe Baſe or Hie:</l>
                  <l>A wanton eye doth guide her wit,</l>
                  <l>and not her wit her Eye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Looſe women doe repine their ſinnes to heare,</l>
                  <l>and folly flings, if counſail touch the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neare.</l>
                  <l>The fooliſh and the wanton women vſe</l>
                  <l>T'obey them moſt, who doth them moſt abuſe.</l>
                  <l>A witleſſe foole &amp; wanton we may gueſſe,</l>
                  <l>that leaues the more, &amp; takes her to the leſſe.</l>
                  <l>When wantons finely ſooth their owne deſires,</l>
                  <l>their beſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceits do proue the greateſt liers.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Liue within Compaſſe: in Temperance.</head>
               <p>ABuſe not thy body in thy youth by Surfet, Riot, or any other
diſtemper <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2065:8"/> through an ouer-weening abilitie of ſtrength;
for youth and Nature paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer many Infirmities that are growing till
their age.</p>
               <p>Liue temperately and vertuouſly, that thou mayſt dye
patiently; for who liues moſt honeſtly, will dye moſt willingly: and for
thy long dayes and better health on earth, afflict not thy body with too much
vnneceſſary Phyſicke, but furniſh thy minde in time of plentie to lay
vp for it ſelfe and others in the time of want; for ſurely her end ſhall
be eaſie and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie that death finde with a weake body, but a ſtrong
Soule.</p>
               <p>Grieue not to groane vnder the hand of ſickneſſe; for as
ſometimes it purgeth the body from intemperate humors, ſo doth it
oftentimes the Soule from more dangerous ſecuritie, and the rather, ſince
there is no perfect health in this world, but a newtralitie betweene
ſickneſſe and health.</p>
               <p>The eyes are the inſtruments of luſt, therefore make a
couenant with them, that they betray not thy heart to vanitie.</p>
               <p>Suffer with thoſe that ſuffer, be cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with thoſe
that are crucified: ſo ſhalt <pb n="12" facs="tcp:2065:9"/> thou be glorified with
thoſe that are glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified.</p>
               <p>True grace and Temperance doe not lift vp, but humble a good
woman; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe is not yet partaker of true grace which doth not walke
in humilitie of heart. The ſtreames of Gods grace doe flow downwards, not
vpwards.</p>
               <p>God creates of nothing, and he repaires of nothing; that
therefore thou maiſt bée partaker of the Regeneration and Repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
be nothing in thine owne eyes, that is, attribute nothing to thy ſelfe,
arrogate nothing to thy ſelfe. Women are weake and fraile; but iudge none
frailer than thy ſelfe: to be inferiour to all, hurts none, to be aboue any,
offends many.</p>
               <p>Temperance is an enemy to luſt, and laſt is an euer-waiting
ſeruant to the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of high bloods.</p>
               <p>Temperance calleth a womun backe from all groſſe affects and
carnall appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, and lets her neither exceed in fooliſh reioycing, nor in
vngodly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing.</p>
               <p>Shee is firmely to be accounted tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, which from the
ground of reaſon can gouerne and bridle the vice of ſenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitie, 
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2065:9"/> and all other groſſe affections of the minde, and
paſſions.</p>
               <p>Temperance is the true Peace-maker in all the tumults betweene
reaſon and paſſion.</p>
               <p>When the vntamed paſſions of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man haue their full
careere, and are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ouer-ruled with Temperance nor diſcretion; then is
the ſoule loſt and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken, or at leaſt, deformed and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;
and the more delicately the body is handled, the more ſtubbornly it
wraſtleth againſt the minde; for the heauie bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of the body is onely
the oppreſſon of the ſoule.</p>
               <p>Shee cannot commend Temperance that imagineth the beſt
felicitie to conſiſt in pleaſure.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>O it is Temperance, with his golden ſquire</l>
                  <l>Between our paſſions, meaſures out a mean,</l>
                  <l>Neither to melt in pleaſures hot deſire,</l>
                  <l>Nor fry in heartleſſe griefe &amp; dolefull teen:</l>
                  <l>Thrice happie ſhee that ſtayes them both betweene.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O in what ſafetie Temperance doth reſt,</l>
                  <l>When it finds harbor in a modeſt breſt.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2065:10"/>Of all Gods workes which doe this world
adorne,</l>
                  <l>There's none more faire, more ſweet or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent</l>
                  <l>Then womans body, both for power and forme,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt it is kept in temperate gouernment.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis harder for to learne faire continence</l>
                  <l>In ioyous pleaſure than in grieuous paine,</l>
                  <l>For ſweetnes doth allure the weaker ſenſe</l>
                  <l>So ſtrongly, that vnneath it can refraine</l>
                  <l>From that which feeble nature couers fain;</l>
                  <l>But griefe and wrath that be her enemies</l>
                  <l>And foes of life, ſhee better can reſtraine,</l>
                  <l>Yet vertue vaunts in both their victories.</l>
                  <l>Let Wolues and Beaſts be cruell in their kinds,</l>
                  <l>But women meeke, and of faire temperate mindes.</l>
                  <l>Though men mindes can couer with bold ſterne lookes,</l>
                  <l>Pale womens faces are their owne faults bookes.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe vertues that in women praiſe doe win,</l>
                  <l>Are ſober ſhewes without, chaſte thoughts within;</l>
                  <l>True faith &amp; due obedience to their make,</l>
                  <l>And of their children honeſt care to take.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:2065:10"/>They melt with words as wax againſt the
Sunne,</l>
                  <l>So weake in many women's modeſtie,</l>
                  <l>For what ſometimes they moſt would ſeeme to
ſhield,</l>
                  <l>Another time vnaskt, poore ſoules they yeeld.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Out of Compaſſe in Temperance. Madneſſe.</head>
               <p>A Mad woman is like a rough ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Horſe, and as he
muſt haue a ſharp bit, ſo muſt ſhee haue a ſharp reſtraint.</p>
               <p>As a blocke though it be decked with gold, pearles, gems, and
precious orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is not to be regarded except it repreſent the ſhape of
ſome thing: euen ſo a woman be ſhe neuer ſo rich and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, yet if
ſhée want obedience, ſhe is of no account or eſtimation.</p>
               <p>Such wiues as would rather haue foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Husbands whom they
might rule, than to be ruled by ſober wiſe men, are like them that would
rather lead a blind <pb n="16" facs="tcp:2065:11"/> man in an vnknowne path, than follow
one that can both ſee and knoweth the way directly.</p>
               <p>She that forſakes her husband becauſe ſhe diſlikes his
manners, is like her that forſakes the Honey leaſt the Bee might ſting
her.</p>
               <p>They which ſacrificed to <hi>Iuno</hi> the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe of
married women, tooke euer the galls from the beaſts which they ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced;
ſignifying thereby, that all anger, madnes, and diſpleaſure ſhould euer
be farre from married couples.</p>
               <p>In three points women and fooles hold ſmall difference; they
are full of vaine affections, they are curious and peeuiſh to pleaſe, and
euer wilfull to diſobay.</p>
               <p>There is no creature that more deſireth honour, and worſe
keepeth it than a mad woman.</p>
               <p>The intemperate woman with her light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and children
with their ſmall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, occupy their minds in things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: but
vertuous wiſe women do thinke on that is paſt, they ordaine for that which
is preſent, and with great ſtudy and care prouide for the time to come.</p>
               <p>There are in outragious womens eyes <pb n="17" facs="tcp:2065:11"/> two
ſeuerall ſorts of teares, the one of griefe, the other of deceit.</p>
               <p>Beautie in womens faces, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in their hearts, are two
wormes which fret life, and waſte goods.</p>
               <p>Mad women for a little goodnes looke for a great recompence, but
for much euill no chaſtiſement.</p>
               <p>A fierce beaſt and a dangerous for is an outragious woman to a
Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: for ſhée hath much power to doe much harme, and is not
apt to follow any goodneſſe.</p>
               <p>A mad woman once defamed beleeues after in no woman vertue, but
defameth all to make her owne vice worthie of a companion.</p>
               <p>The tongue of a mad woman is a ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie inſtrument, nimble
to doe miſchiefe; for commonly by it friendſhip is decayed, worldly riches
diminiſhed, the life moſt miſerably waſted, and infamy and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
paine purchaſed.</p>
               <p>Such a miſchieuous euill is the ſinne of detraction in the
heart of a proud and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly woman, that there is neither long familiarilie,
accuſtomed fellowſhip, nor cauſes of approued friendſhip, neither yet 
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2065:12"/> any eſtate or degree that can once bridle them, or
ſtay them from doing infinite miſchiefe.</p>
               <p>She that is giuen to the vice of detrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is worthily
ſubiect to the common hatred of men, and to be eſchewed of all as a moſt
peſtilent infection; and at her enterance into any place among good women,
euery mouth to be either ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped againſt her, or otherwiſe opened to
hiſſe her out of doores, as a thing altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther voyde of delight, and
filled vp but with danger onely.</p>
               <p>Amongſt temperate women, madde women are made bright; but
amongſt madde women, temperate women are made glorious.</p>
               <p>It is a great madneſſe in any woman to amuſe vpon thoſe
things which are farre beyond her vnderſtanding.</p>
               <p>A faire woman without diſcretion, is like a faire houſe and
an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>uill hoſt har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bored
therein.</p>
               <p>Many times of wiſe maides becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth fooliſh wantons, and of
fooliſh wantons, wiſe maides.</p>
               <p>Let euery woman behold her ſelfe in a Looking-glaſſe, and
if ſhee appeare <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2065:12"/> beautifull, let her doe ſuch things as
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come her beautie; but if ſhée ſéeme foule, then let her
make good with good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners the beautie which her face lacketh.</p>
               <p>As the body being alwayes oppreſt with labour loſeth his
ſtrength, and ſo periſheth; ſo doth the minde of a woman oppreſſed
with paſſions and pleaſures of this world, loſe the force, luſt, and
deſire which ſhee had to the reſt of eternall life to come.</p>
               <p>Exceſſe of paſſions may euer hurt, they can neuer
profit.</p>
               <p>When ſenſualitie reigneth, (eſpecially amongſt women)
there reaſon taketh no place.</p>
               <p>A madde Woman knoweth things done, but a diſcreet woman
conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth things long before they come to paſſe.</p>
               <p>Praiſe and indiſcretion can neuer be coupled together.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>From idle wit there ſprings a brain-ſick will,</l>
                  <l>Which wiſe men luſt, which fooliſh make a god;</l>
                  <l>This in the ſhape of vertue reigneth ſtill,</l>
                  <l>But 'tis the onely vice, one worſt and odde.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:2065:13"/>Will puts in practice what the wit
deuiſeth;</l>
                  <l>Will euer acts, and wit contemplates ſtill,</l>
                  <l>And as from wit the power of wiſedome riſeth,</l>
                  <l>All other vertues daughters are of will.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The heedleſſe will true iudgement doth enſnare,</l>
                  <l>Who's rul'd by it doth neuer want her care.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where womens actions meaſure no regard,</l>
                  <l>There lawleſſe will is made his owne regard.</l>
                  <l>Such is the crueltie of women kinde,</l>
                  <l>When they haue maken off the ſhame-fac't band,</l>
                  <l>With which wiſe nature did them ſtrongly binde</l>
                  <l>T'obey the heſts of mans well-ruling hand,</l>
                  <l>That then all rule &amp; reaſon they withſtand,</l>
                  <l>To purchaſe a licentious libertie:</l>
                  <l>But vertuous women wiſely vnderſtand,</l>
                  <l>That they were borne to baſe humilitie,</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe the Heauens them lift to lawfull
ſouereigntie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What iron band, or what ſharp mouthed bit,</l>
                  <l>What chain of Diamond; if ſuch might be,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:2065:13"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an bridle womens wrath, or conquer it,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd keepe them in
their bounds, and true degree?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Craft makes a woman oft appeare in ſhow,</l>
                  <l>Merry and ſad, when ſhee is neuer ſo.</l>
                  <l>The louely lookes, the ſighs that ſtorme ſo ſore,</l>
                  <l>The due of deep diſſembling doubtfulneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Theſe may attempt, but are of power no more,</l>
                  <l>When beauty leanes to wit &amp; ſoothfaſtnes.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Liue within Compaſſe: in Beautie.</head>
               <p>THere is nothing harder for a woman than to know her ſelfe;
for blinded with beautie and ſelfe-loue, they flatter themſelues in all
things.</p>
               <p>There is in euery woman two pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, which draw and conduct her;
a deſire of pleaſure bred in the beautie of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and a good opinion
coueting onely good things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> betweene theſe two there is continuall
ſtrife in women, and when <pb n="22" facs="tcp:2065:14"/> the opinion hath the
maiſtry, it maketh a woman ſober, chaſte, diſcreet, &amp; quiet: but
when deſire getteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vpper hand, it makes her luſtfull, riotous,
couetous, &amp; vnquiet.</p>
               <p>Three things a woman ought to hold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, her ſoule, her
body, the ſubſtance of this world: The ſoule firſt, becauſe it is a
thing beautifull, &amp; immortall, made after the ſhape of God himſelfe:
The body next becauſe it is faire, and is the caſe and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher of the
ſoule, and the neareſt ſeruant to the ſecret ſpirit: laſtly the
ſubſtance of this world being neceſſary, and the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall
inſtruments and tools of the body. Let then the eyes of euery womans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
minde firſt reſpect the beautie of her ſoule, then the comelineſſe of
her body, and laſtly, the neceſſitie of riches.</p>
               <p>She that loueth beautie more than ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, ſhall either lack
that ſhe coueteth, or els loſe what ſhe hath got with great paine.</p>
               <p>Shée that is in loue with her owne beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is like one
that trauelleth on the Seas; if ſhe eſcape the dangers (which are
ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals) ſhee is fortunate, but if ſhée periſh, ſhee is
wilfully deceiued.</p>
               <p>Truſt not beautie, for it neuer payeth what it
promiſeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:2065:14"/>Beautie in this world is the delight of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n houre, and the ſorrow of many
dayes; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut in the world to come,
eternall reſt and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ong ioy.</p>
               <p>Beautie is of two ſorts, as of the body, which is a
ſéemly compoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, wherein all the parts with a
certain grace agree together; and the other of the winde, which is a
conueniency meet for the excellency of man or woman, and that wherin their
nature doth differ from other liuing creatures; &amp; as the outward beauty
moueth &amp; reioiceth the eies, ſo this ſhining in their liues by order
&amp; moderation, both in deeds &amp; words, draweth vnto them the hearts of
them amongſt whom they liue.</p>
               <p>Beauty is ſuch a fading good, that it can be ſcarce
poſſeſſed, before it be vaniſhed.</p>
               <p>The greateſt gift that euer heauen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on a woman, is
beautie; for it both delighteth the eye, contenteth the minde, &amp; winneth
good fauour of all men.</p>
               <p>The beauty of the body withereth with age, and is impaired by
ſickneſſe, but the beautie of the ſoule, which is innocency and
humilitie, can neuer be conſumed.</p>
               <p>A beautifull countenance is a ſilent commendations.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:2065:15"/>The faireſt creature that euer Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> created was the world.</p>
               <p>Beautie, honor, and wealth, are thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> deepe perſwaſions to make loue
frollick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and men miſerable.</p>
               <p>In all things diuiſible there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing more,
ſomething leſſe, ſomethin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
equall more or leſſe: what can be more e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quall than beautie or wit?</p>
               <p>The Scorpion if hee touch neuer ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lightly, inuenometh the whole body; th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leaſt ſparke of wild-fire ſets
the whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> houſe on a flame, the
Cockatrice kils me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with his
ſight, the ſting of loue and beauti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> woundeth deadly, the flame of fancy ſet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all the thoughts on fire, and the eyes of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> louer wounded with beautie, are
accoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted incurable.</p>
               <p>Shée that is an enemy to beautie is a fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to nature, and ſhée that
doats on beauti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is a high traytor
to nature.</p>
               <p>Beauties that ſhould be concealed, too groſly diſcouered,
are faire ſignes hung out to entice to an vnhoſpitable Inne.</p>
               <p>Beautie without honeſty is poyſon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in a box of
gold.</p>
               <p>Let not a womans beauty, but her ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue be her dower, for her
good deeds will <pb n="25" facs="tcp:2065:15"/> remaine when age hath taken her beautie
from her.</p>
               <p>Let no woman ſtriue to excell in beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, but hold the golden
meane, which is the true mediocritie and beſt part of any action, and muſt
be vſed in all things: it containeth the full effects of prudence tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
gouernment, and tranquilitie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſoule.</p>
               <p>Curioſitie and extremity baniſhed wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man from the firſt
modeſty of her nature.</p>
               <p>To liue on the mountaines, and haue too much heat, is to be
Sunne-burnt; to liue in the valley and haue too little, is barren; to hold the
meane is euer moſt fruitfull.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>'Tis ſacred Beautie is the fruit of ſight,</l>
                  <l>The curteſie that ſpeaks before the tongue,</l>
                  <l>The feaſt of ſoules, the glory of the lights,</l>
                  <l>Enuy of age, and euerlaſting young,</l>
                  <l>Pitties commander, <hi>Cupids</hi> richeſt throne,</l>
                  <l>Muſicke entranced, neuer dully ſung:</l>
                  <l>The ſumme and court of all proportion.</l>
                  <l>And that I may dull ſpeeches leaſt afford,</l>
                  <l>All Rhetorickes flowers in leſſe than a word.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:2065:16"/>'Tis beauty that is a womans golden
crown,</l>
                  <l>Mans conquereſſe, and feminine renowne,</l>
                  <l>Not ioynd with loue, who deare yet euer ſold it?</l>
                  <l>For Beauty's cheape, except loues eye behold it.</l>
                  <l>Beautie is ſtill an Adamant to all,</l>
                  <l>And Natures buſh that paſſengers doth call.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Beautie it ſelfe doth of it ſelfe perſwade</l>
                  <l>The eyes of men without an Orator:</l>
                  <l>What needeth then Apologies be made,</l>
                  <l>To ſet forth that which is ſo ſingular?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O how can Beauty maſter the moſt ſtrong,</l>
                  <l>And ſimple Truth ſubdue aue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging wrong?</l>
                  <l>O what is he whoſe youth can ſay he loues not,</l>
                  <l>Or who ſo old that womens beauty moues not?</l>
                  <l>Neuer were cheeks of roſes, locks of amber</l>
                  <l>Ordaind to liue impriſon'd in a chamber.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Heauen made Beauty like it ſelfe to view,</l>
                  <l>Not to be lockt vp in a ſmokie mew:</l>
                  <l>A roſie vertuous cheeke is heauens gold,</l>
                  <l>Which all men ioy to touch, all to behold.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:2065:16"/>The ripeſt corne dyes if it be not
reapt,</l>
                  <l>Beauty alone is loſt too char'ly kept.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Out of Compaſſe in Beautie, Odiouſneſſe.</head>
               <p>TO exceed Nature or thy condition, is a ryotous exceſſe in
luſt, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, or other ornament, it is alſo a part of pride, and
contrary to decency and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</p>
               <p>Exceſſe of brauery brings a woman of wealth quickly to
pouertie, and exceſſe of beautie to hate and odiouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>They that rather delight to decke their bodies than their
ſoules, ſeeme women rather created for their bodies than their
ſoules.</p>
               <p>As the wéed cannot be eſteemed preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for the faire
flower which it beareth, ſo ought no woman to be accounted ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous for the
gay garment ſhée weareth, or the beauty ſhée borroweth.</p>
               <p>Beautie may be ouerthrowne with age, <pb n="28" facs="tcp:2065:17"/> and
apparell conſumed with moaths: what folly is it then for women to delight in
that which an houre can waſte, or a very little worme deſtroy?</p>
               <p>Raine can neuer cauſe the Corne to bring forth any fruit which
is ſowne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hard ſtones, nor ſpeech cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade a proud woman
to become an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to braue apparell.</p>
               <p>Gorgeous garments are markes of pride, and neſts of
riotouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>As a man would iudge one to be ill at eaſe which weareth a
plaſter vpon his face, or one that hath beene ſcourged to be puniſhed by
the Law; ſo doth painting betoken in a woman, a diſeaſed ſoule mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
with adultery.</p>
               <p>As it is no wiſedome in admiring the ſcabard to deſpiſe
the blade, ſo is it meere folly to praiſe a woman for her brauery, &amp;
diſcommend her for her modeſty.</p>
               <p>Odious is that beautie which ſleepeth not with the face.</p>
               <p>If by the ciuill Law the child may haue an action of the caſe
againſt him which ſhall deface the portraiture of his father, we may well
imagine what action God will haue againſt thoſe women which by 
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2065:17"/> artificiall painting, ſeeke to correct his
workmanſhip.</p>
               <p>Painting haſtens wrinkles before old age come.</p>
               <p>All kinde of painting, artificiall gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing, and colouring
of haire, was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden among the Spartans, deſpiſed of wiſe men, and
loathed of good men.</p>
               <p>There are three things which coſt dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and conſume
quickly; a faire woman that is vnchaſte, a rich garment that hath many cuts,
and a wealthy ſtocke in the hands of an ill husband.</p>
               <p>The tongue of a bitter woman pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth deeper than her eyes.</p>
               <p>A painted womans ſorrowes, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer extreme, ought not to
be redreſſed: for being trimmed vp with diſſimulation, ſhe ſhould
not be beleeued.</p>
               <p>A painted womans eyes haue two ſorts of teares, the one of
ſorrow, the other of diſſimulation.</p>
               <p>Falſe beautie in the faces of women, &amp; folly in their
heads, are two wormes that fretteth life, and waſteth goods.</p>
               <p>Ill women for little goodneſſe looke for great praiſe, but
for much euill no cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:2065:18"/>A fierce beaſt and a dangerous enemy to
the common-wealth is a wicked wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, for ſhee is of much power to doe much
harme.</p>
               <p>An ill womans heart is full of holes, apt to receiue, but not to
retaine.</p>
               <p>He that can endure a curſt wife, needs not feare the Deuill
for his companion.</p>
               <p>The cloſet of a bad womans thought is euer open, and the depth
of her heart hath a ſtring that ſtretcheth to her tongues end.</p>
               <p>A painted womans face is a liuer ſmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with carrion, her
beauty baits of dead wormes, her lookes nets, and her words inticing
charmes.</p>
               <p>An vnconſtant faire woman may bée likened to
<hi>Praſiteles</hi> Picture which hee made of <hi>Flora,</hi> before which if
one ſtood directly, it ſeemed to weepe; if on the left ſide, it ſeemed
to laugh; if on the right ſide, to ſleepe.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>A ſparke of beautie burnes a world of creatures,</l>
                  <l>When it is of ſophiſticated features.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O beauty, ſtill thine Empire ſwims in blood</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:2065:18"/>And in thy peace warre ſtores himſelfe
of food.</l>
                  <l>Beautie a begger, fie it is too bad,</l>
                  <l>When in it ſelfe ſufficiency is had:</l>
                  <l>It was not made to pleaſe the wandring eie,</l>
                  <l>But an attire t'adorne ſweet modeſty.</l>
                  <l>If modeſty and women once doe ſeuer,</l>
                  <l>Farewell all fame, farewell all name for euer.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O beautie that betrayes thy ſelfe to euery amorous eye,</l>
                  <l>To trap thy proud profeſſors, what is it but wantons
try?</l>
                  <l>Where through it ſeldome haps, the faire from meane deceits
to flye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Truce, war, and woe, doe wait at beauties gate,</l>
                  <l>Time loſt, laments, reports, &amp; priuy grudge,</l>
                  <l>And laſt fierce loue is but a partiall iudge,</l>
                  <l>Who yeelds for ſeruice ſhame, for friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip hate.</l>
                  <l>The Bees of Hybla haue beſides ſweet honey, ſmarting
ſtings;</l>
                  <l>And Beautie doth not want a bait that to repentance
brings.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:2065:19"/>The faireſt cheeke hath oftentimes a
ſoule</l>
                  <l>Leprous as ſin it ſelfe, than hell more foule.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Liue within Compaſſe: in Humilitie.</head>
               <p>SHee that gathereth vertues without Humilitie, caſteth duſt
againſt the winde, and loſeth her labour.</p>
               <p>Happie is that woman whoſe calling is great, and her ſpirit
humble.</p>
               <p>Humilitie is a twinne to Chaſtitie and Nobilitie, and as
neceſſary in a woman as her virginitie.</p>
               <p>Nothing can repaire a decayed Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie but true
Humilitie.</p>
               <p>Since the Countrey which a woman deſires to dwell in, is high
and heauenly, and the way thither Lowlineſſe and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, why then
deſiring this Countrey, ſhould they refuſe the way?</p>
               <p>There are three degrees of Humilitie: the firſt, of
Repentance; the ſecond, a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Righteouſneſſe; and the third,
the workes of mercy.</p>
               <p>Shée that cannot haue what ſhée would, 
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2065:19"/> muſt be humbly content with what ſhee can get.</p>
               <p>Sufferance maketh women Angels, but pride maketh them
Deuils.</p>
               <p>Let not thankes waxe old, when gifts are in thy
poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>She that refuſeth to buy good counſell cheape, ſhall buy
repentance deare.</p>
               <p>Mocke not at any in miſery, but by it auoid the like
miſfortune.</p>
               <p>Giue no vaine and vnneceſſary gifts, as is Armour to thy
maids, Bookes to thy plow-ſwaine, or Nets to a Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</p>
               <p>Let thy beſt apparell be Iuſtice, and thy vppermoſt
garment Chaſtitie; ſo ſhalt thou be happy, and thy dayes proſper.</p>
               <p>Let Vertue be thy life, Humilitie thy loue, Honour thy fame, and
Heauen thy felicitie.</p>
               <p>Let not thy bounty exceed thy meanes, nor thy free mind thy
modeſty, kéepe thine eye in equall pace with thine eare, and thy
tongue ſhort of thy feet.</p>
               <p>Rather liue wal'd vp with an Ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, than houſ'd with an
euill woman.</p>
               <p>Be not ſecure, leſt want of care pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure thy calamitie; nor
too carefull, leſt <pb n="34" facs="tcp:2065:20"/> penſiue thoughts oppreſſe thee
with miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
               <p>Behold thy ſelfe in a Looking-glaſſe, and if thou appeare
beautifull, doe ſuch things as becomes thy beautie; but if thou ſeeme
foule, then performe with good manners the dutie which thy face wanteth.</p>
               <p>If thy Parents waxe poore, ſupply their want with thy wealth;
if froward with age, beare patiently with their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections.</p>
               <p>Liue and hope as if thou wert not to liue a moment.</p>
               <p>Neuer wiſh impoſſible wiſhes, for it expreſſeth but
a wanton paſſion, or a moſt greedy couetouſneſſe, both grounded on
folly.</p>
               <p>To friuolous queſtions ſilence is euer the beſt
anſwer.</p>
               <p>Beware what thou granteſt in any ſort, for inconueniences
follow one in the necke of the other.</p>
               <p>If thou doubt in any thing, aske counſell of the wiſe, and
be not angry at their reproofe, leaſt (as <hi>Martiall</hi> the Poet ſaid)
it be truth that thou loueſt, not truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:2065:20"/>Shée that talketh much to little
purpoſe, is like him that ſailes with a ſide-winde, and is borne to a
wrong ſhoare.</p>
               <p>As a woman without humilitie is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant, ſo humilitie
without ſeueritie draweth neare to proſtitution.</p>
               <p>She only may properly be called a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that in her behauiour
gouerneth her ſelfe like a woman, that is to ſay, conformable to ſuch
things as reaſon willeth, and not as the motions of ſenſualitie
requireth.</p>
               <p>Where any demand is a ieſt, the fitteſt anſwer is a
ſcoffe.</p>
               <p>Rather labour to be deliuered from contempt, than practiſe to
be reuenged.</p>
               <p>The eye can neuer offend if the minde would rule the eye, but
where there is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, there is euer confuſion.</p>
               <p>Solitarineſſe is the onely ſlie enemy that ſeparateth
both woman and man from doing well.</p>
               <p>Liking is not alwayes the childe of beautie, but iealouſie is
euer the buſie har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benger to diſdaine.</p>
               <p>Shee that will needs ſtirre affections in others, muſt
firſt ſhew the ſame paſſion in her ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Shee that blameth another, muſt <pb n="36" facs="tcp:2065:21"/> firſt
be blameleſſe her ſelfe, eſpecially in the matter ſhe blameth another
for.</p>
               <p>Forbearance of ſpeech is moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous when neceſſitie
requireth to ſpeake.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Humilitie is aged, hoary, gray,</l>
                  <l>With looke full lowly caſt, and gate full ſlowe:</l>
                  <l>Who on a ſtaffe his ſteps doth ſtay,</l>
                  <l>To whom who comes muſt euer ſtoope moſt low;</l>
                  <l>For ſtrait and narrow is the way that he doth ſhow.</l>
                  <l>Humilitie to heauen is ſtep and ſtaire,</l>
                  <l>Both for deuotion, ſacrifice, and prayer.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The bending knee in ſafetie ſtill doth goe,</l>
                  <l>when others ſtumble, as too ſtiffe to bow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah, God ſhield maid, that any one</l>
                  <l>ſhould learne to looke aloft:</l>
                  <l>This reed is rife, that oftentimes</l>
                  <l>great climbers fall vnſoft.</l>
                  <l>In humble dales is footing faſt,</l>
                  <l>the troad is not ſo tickle:</l>
                  <l>And though one fall through heedles haſt,</l>
                  <l>yet is his miſſe not mickle.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:2065:21"/>As on th'vnſauory ſtock the Lilly's
borne,</l>
                  <l>And as the Roſe growes on the pricking thorne:</l>
                  <l>So modeſt life, with ſobs of glorious ſmart,</l>
                  <l>And cryes deuout, comes from an humble heart.</l>
                  <l>More honor's in humilitie,</l>
                  <l>than ſafetie is in wals:</l>
                  <l>Ill liuers proue not monuments,</l>
                  <l>ſaue onely in their falls.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Meekneſſe this noble vertue and diuine,</l>
                  <l>Doth make a woman ſtill ſo rare and od,</l>
                  <l>As in that one ſhe moſt reſembleth God.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Euer as rage kindleth the fire of wrath,</l>
                  <l>Meeknes to quench it ſtore of water hath.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Out of Compaſſe in Humilitie, Pride.</head>
               <p>PRide perceiuing Humilitie to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, deſires
oftentimes to bée couered with her garment, for feare leaſt appearing
alwayes in her owne likeneſſe, <pb n="38" facs="tcp:2065:22"/> ſhe ſhould be
little regarded.</p>
               <p>Immoderate wealth cauſeth pride, pride bringeth hatred, hatred
worketh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, rebellion maketh an alteration and changeth Kingdomes, euen
in wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens diſſentions.</p>
               <p>That kind of fantaſticke contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which tends to
ſolitarineſſe, is but a glorious title to proud idleneſſe.</p>
               <p>The proud conceit of young women, is, that they can ſpeake
wiſely, when they cannot vnderſtand themſelues.</p>
               <p>When Dogs fall on ſnarling, Serpents on hiſſing, and Women
on weeping, the firſt meanes to bite, the ſecond to ſting, and the laſt
to deceiue.</p>
               <p>As rewards are neceſſary for well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſo
chaſtiſements are meet for proud offenders.</p>
               <p>Pride is alwayes accompanied with Folly, Audacitie,
Raſhneſſe, Impudency, and Solitarineſſe: as if one would ſay that
the proud woman is abandoned of all the world, euer attributing that to her
ſelfe which is not, hauing much more boaſt than matter of worth.</p>
               <p>Pride did firſt ſpring in men from too much abundance of
wealth, in women <pb n="39" facs="tcp:2065:22"/> from too much truſt in beautie, and the
flattery of men.</p>
               <p>Pride is the mother of Enuie; ſtrangle her, and her daughter
dieth.</p>
               <p>She that knowes her ſelfe beſt, will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer eſteeme her
ſelfe leaſt.</p>
               <p>It is hard for a faire woman not to be proud.</p>
               <p>A proud woman is like <hi>Theocritus</hi> his fiſherman;
ſhée onely feeds the vanitie of her fancy with dreames of gold.</p>
               <p>If a mans folly make a woman once his equall, her pride will
ſoone make her ſelfe his ſuperior.</p>
               <p>Women be of ſo tender condition, that they will complaine for
a ſmall cauſe, and for a leſſe will riſe vp into infinite pride.</p>
               <p>There is no creature that more deſires honour, worſe
kéeps it, and ſooner loſeth it, than a proud woman.</p>
               <p>Proud women in miſchiefe are euer wiſer than men.</p>
               <p>It is naturall to a proud woman, to deſpiſe that which is
offered her; and death to her to be denied any thing ſhée
deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sophocles</hi> being asked, why, when he brought in the
perſons of women, hee <pb n="40" facs="tcp:2065:23"/> made them alwayes good, whereas
<hi>Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pides</hi> made them all bad: Becauſe (quoth he) I preſent women
as they ſhould be, and <hi>Euripides</hi> preſented them ſuch as they
are.</p>
               <p>A proud womans will is like a Sheffild knife, ſometimes ſo
ſharpe it will cut a haire, and otherwhiles ſo blunt it muſt needs goe to
the grindſtone.</p>
               <p>If women be beautifull, they are to be won with prayſes; if
coy, with prayers; if proud, with gifts; if wonton, with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; but if
good, with prouidence and vertue.</p>
               <p>Thoſe women which eſteeme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues moſt wiſe, are
euermore the ſooneſt tickled with ſelfe-loue.</p>
               <p>A proud womans mind is euer vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: it hath as many new
deuices as a tree hath leaues, for ſhée is alwayes deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of
change, and ſeldome loueth him heartily with whom ſhee hath beene long
conuerſant.</p>
               <p>Truſt not a proud woman when ſhee weepeth, for it is her
nature to ſhed teares when ſhée wants her will.</p>
               <p>A proud woman in her wit is pregnable, in her ſmile
deceiuable, in her frowne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uengeable, <pb n="41" facs="tcp:2065:23"/> and laſtly in
her death accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of griſly <hi>Pluto,</hi> Pride the daughter was,</l>
                  <l>And ſad <hi>Proſerpina</hi> the Queene of hell,</l>
                  <l>Yet doth ſhe thinke her pearles worthy to paſſe,</l>
                  <l>That pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage with pride ſo doth ſhe ſwell;</l>
                  <l>And thundring <hi>Ioue</hi> that hie in heauen doth dwell,</l>
                  <l>And wield the world, ſhee claimed for her fire;</l>
                  <l>Or if that any elſe doth <hi>Ioue</hi> excell,</l>
                  <l>For to the higheſt ſhe doth ſtill aſpire;</l>
                  <l>Or if ought higher were, then that doth ſhe deſire.</l>
                  <l>O pride the ſhelf cloſe ſhrouded in the port</l>
                  <l>Of this lifes Ocean, drowning all reſort.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Pride makes her rounds, for ſhee hath neuer end,</l>
                  <l>And Soners, for ſhe neuer leaues her noiſe:</l>
                  <l>She makes her dumps, if any thing offend,</l>
                  <l>And to her idoll ſelfe, with warbling voice,</l>
                  <l>Sings Hyms &amp; Anthems of eſpeciall choice:</l>
                  <l>And yet prides quire's put to ſilence clean,</l>
                  <l>Wanting a Baſe, a Tenor, and a Meane,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:2065:24"/>Pride is the ſcourge of ſin, the
Deuils fee,</l>
                  <l>The head of hell, the bough, the branch, the tree.</l>
                  <l>From which doe ſpring and ſprout ſuch fleſhly
ſeeds,</l>
                  <l>As nothing elſe but moane and miſchiefe breeds.</l>
                  <l>Such is the nature ſtill of haughtie pride,</l>
                  <l>Can nothing leſſe than others praiſe abide.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A proud maid may her owne muſitian be,</l>
                  <l>Her heads deuice makes pauens to her heart</l>
                  <l>This hart with lips &amp; pleaſures da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth free,</l>
                  <l>All but the meaſures framing euery part;</l>
                  <l>Like Organs worthy of ſo ſweet an Art,</l>
                  <l>Her thoughts playes marches on her vaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting mind,</l>
                  <l>And Memory her Recorder ſtands behind.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2065:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
